<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eng-415-145a"><body><div><head><pb facs="#f000"/> The Desolate Valley. A South-African Scene. By Thomas Pringle</head>
				<p>
					<add>145a 1</add>
				</p>
				<p><add rend="pen" resp="tp" type="authorial">[The</add> result of the Caffer war of 1819-20 ^<add rend="caret" type="authorial">between the Colonial Government of the Cape and &amp; the Caffer tribes</add> was the annexation to the Colo<add>ny</add> of a large track of the Amakosa country<del rend="strikethrough" resp="personography#pringle-t" type="authorial">, extending to about two millions of acres</del>. This was affected by a compulsory convention with the native chiefs <del rend="strikethrough" resp="personography#pringle-t" type="authorial">(our <hi rend="italic">ally</hi> Gaika included),</del> who, with their followers, were <del rend="strikethrough" resp="personography#pringle-t" type="authorial">then</del> dislodged and expelled beyond the Keisi and Chumi rivers. The whole of the evacuated territory, under the appellation of the Neutral Ground, remained unoccupied for several years, and a large portion of it remains so still. I made an excursion through part of it, from the Winterberg mountain down the river Koonap, in 1822, <del rend="strikethrough" resp="personography#pringle-t" type="authorial">in company with Captain (now Colonel) C. R. Fox and some other officers,</del> and again, in 1825, in another direction. The aspect of the country, though wild, was beautiful and impossible; it was finely diversified with lofty mountains and winding glens, with picturesque rocks and forests, open upland pastures, and level savannas along the rivers, sprinkled with mimosa-trees: and herds of wild animals, quaggas, elands, hartebeests, gnu<add rend="caret-above" resp="personography#pringle-t" type="authorial">o</add>s, koodoos, with many varieties of the smaller antelopes, were scattered over the verdant pastures; while troops of elephants were browsing undisturbed among the wooded kloofs and jungles of evergreens. But the remains of Caffer hamlets, scattered through every grassy nook and dell, and now long deserted and fast crumbling to decay, excited reflections of no gratifying character, and occasionally increased, even to a painful degree, the feeling of melancholy <hi rend="italic">lonesomeness</hi> which a country void of human inhabitants never fails to inspire. Before the Caffers ^<add rend="marginal-caret" resp="personography#pringle-t" type="authorial">and Ghonaquas</add> were expelled from this territory, a few of them had acquired some knowledge of Christianity, partly from the instructions of that singular but most meritorious man Dr. Vanderkemp, and more especially from the missionary Williams, who resided about two years among them at the Kat River, previous to his death in 1818<add rend="inline" resp="personography#pringle-t" type="authorial">.</add> <add rend="inline" resp="personography#pringle-t" type="authorial">The following stanzas are an attempt to give a sketch of a remote vale in this wild country, after the first missionary station had been left desolate, &amp; previous to its occupation by the Emancipated Hottentots &amp; their Christian Pastors in 1829.]</add></p>
				<lg>
					<l>Far up among the forest-belted mountains,</l>
					<l>Where Winterberg, stern giant old &amp; grey,</l>
					<l>Looks down the subject dells, whose gleaming fountains</l>
					<l>To Wizard Kat their virgin tribute pay,</l>
					<l>A valley opens to the moontide ray,</l>
					<l>With green Savannahs shelving to the brim</l>
					<l>Of the young River, sweeping on his way</l>
					<l>To where Umtoka hies to meet with him,</l>
					<l>Like a blue serpent gliding through the acacias dim.</l>
				</lg>
				<lg>
					<label n="2" type="stanza-num"/></lg></div></body></text>